Disembodied human brains, kept alive
postmortem in a vat. There's not a lot
of things that I look at in science and
just immediately say no, we should not
be doing this, but this is one of them
and it is fascinating. I did have to
stare at a wall for a little while and
decide how I wanted to talk about this
one. In 2019, researchers shocked the
world when they revived pig brains 4
hours postmortem. They restored
circulation and some dull activity,
global cell activity was in fact
restored, but consciousness was not and
they've taken their vision one step
further and revived human brains. The
company is called NeXorg. They are the
creators of the BrainX platform. They
raised over $42 million for this
research. They've also experimented with
over 700 human brains, so an awful lot
of people have agreed to this. This dude
could end up being a platform for
computation because we have found out
that you can do computation with a human
brain and this is very much the same
idea, just using the outputs of medical
trials as information to process. I
really don't want to see living human
brains becoming a form of computation. I
mean, the brain organoids were weird
enough. Fortunately, I don't think this
is as valuable to learn new skills the
way that brain organoids learn them.
Now, brain in a vat was supposed to be a
philosophical conversation because how
can we ever know that we are truly
experiencing the world when we are in
fact brains inside of a skull and we
rely on external input to tell us what's
there. Well, that has been turned into a
real life thing. That is a real vat with
a real brain in it. 24 hours ago, that
was a person. Now, the researchers did
state that the brains are under heavy
sedation, so even if there were any
consciousness, which there shouldn't be,
we have essentially reached the point of
brain death. Well, they wouldn't really
be experiencing anything, although their
vision has removing the anesthesia so
that they can work with them. This
should help the development of
medication. It gives us a model that we
can work with that is actually a human
brain that can be kept alive. Currently,
they're only alive for the short term,
although they are looking to extend it
to weeks, possibly longer. Now, this has
some great advantages over organoids,
which are one of my favorite science
oddities. Yes, you can grow a tiny
version of a human brain using stem
cells. However, the organoids, well,
yes, they can be kept alive for years,
they have the drawbacks that they are
essentially infants. Yes, their gene
activity matches their chronological
age. So, even if you keep them alive for
5 years or more, they essentially have
the gene expression of a 5-year-old
brain. If you take human brains from a
human that has been alive for feasibly
60 or 80 years, you then have aged
cells. So, you can see how aged cells
will interact when you do stuff to them.
Yes, it actually has a great deal of
scientific merit, but it's also really
creepy. That system is operating as a
synthetic body. This is something that
we just have not invented for brain
organoids yet. It already has all the
structures in the brain that should
cooperate with the body. It has
synthetic lungs that exchange oxygen
with the air that is delivered by a
synthetic heart and a synthetic
circulatory system. But, since the brain
was grown inside a human feasibly, it
has all of the structures to receive
those nutrients.
Like brain organoids, it also is covered
in sensors, so we can figure out what's
going on inside of the brain. People who
donated these brains were usually
elderly and usually had some
deteriorating condition like Parkinson's
or Alzheimer's. This means that we can
treat the brains for these conditions
and figure out how well medications
would work on a person. This is a huge
advantage over mouse models and even
brain organoid models, which again,
model essentially a baby brain. Now, you
may ask, and reasonably so, who would
agree to this? Well, these were people
who already donated their bodies to
science, and family members had to agree
to potentially treat this condition down
the line so someone else doesn't have to
suffer with it. These systems can
potentially answer an enormous subset of
questions, including what happens to
your brain after you expire. What are
the experiences like? When do the
experiences stop? I do want to say that
finding out that they use heavy sedation
for the brains is encouraging. Finding
out that there are limitations with the
use of sedation, and we may not be able
to study everything using it, is less
encouraging. This does, however, give me
some interesting ideas, which is, you
know, never a good sign, because I
wonder if we are getting closer to the
point where we could do a brain
transplant. We know that the brain
organoids can do things like operate
robots. Perhaps we are looking at a
future where we have mechanized bodies
and transplanted brains. I mean, it's
not out of the realm of possibility, and
I really would have thought this was out
of the realm of possibility.
One of the things that bothers me about
this is that how can someone withdraw
consent? Say that some consciousness is
present. We don't have evidence for that
right now, but these machines could
improve.
How could they say now, "No, they don't
want it?" Yeah. That that bothers me.
You might be comforted to know, as I am
comforted, that this is not the end goal
for the brains, although a whole lot of
technology probably will come from it.
They all want to build a model of a
brain. Yes, a synthetic one. This is an
area of science called digital twins,
where researchers work with a synthetic
version of an animal or a person, rather
than the actual animal. So, if you want
to test development of a medication on a
synthetic brain, yes, that is within the
realm of possibility. That might sound
ridiculous, that we could model a brain
with such efficacy that it would be
indistinguishable from a human brain,
and no, that is not impossible. Many
researchers are working on it. The thing
that keeps me up at night is that if we
could really model a brain, model a
person, make something that is so
similar to a person that it is
indistinguishable in reactions, in
actions, how is that not a person? It's
a simulation of a person. Therefore, no
suffering is actually happening. We
could just simulate suffering. I think
we are rapidly approaching the point at
which those questions will need to be
answered, and it will be very
interesting at the point in which an AI
model of a person or some other
intelligent entity decides to start
asking questions, and we have to decide
what we are going to answer. I hope one
of the questions is not, "Why did you
make me?"
I hope you've enjoyed this information
because I have to go stare at a wall for
a while longer. I do not know how I feel
about this yet. Follow for more of the
cutting edge. You know I'll bring it.